<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="weft_shell_unstable_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright (C) 2026 WEFT OS contributors

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining
    a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the
    "Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction, including
    without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish,
    distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to
    permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to
    the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the
    next paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions
    of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
    NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE
    LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION
    OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION
    WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="WEFT compositor–shell protocol">
    This protocol defines the boundary between weft-compositor and
    weft-servo-shell. It allows the shell to manage window slots on behalf
    of application surfaces that the compositor owns.

    The shell binds the weft_shell_manager_v1 global once per connection.
    The manager creates weft_shell_window_v1 objects, each representing one
    visual window slot. The compositor is authoritative for geometry,
    focus, and stacking. The shell is authoritative for window metadata,
    chrome layout, and the decision to create or destroy a window slot.

    Warning: This protocol is unstable and subject to change before version
    1 is finalized. Clients must check the version advertised by the
    compositor and handle unknown events gracefully.
  </description>

  <!-- ───────────────────────────── Manager ───────────────────────────── -->

  <interface name="zweft_shell_manager_v1" version="1">

    <description summary="shell session manager">
      Bound once by weft-servo-shell. The manager owns the shell session.
      If the binding is destroyed the compositor invalidates all window
      objects that were created through it.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager and end the shell session">
        Destroys the manager. All weft_shell_window_v1 objects created
        through this manager become inert. The compositor will emit
        window_closed on each before processing the destructor.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_window">
      <description summary="create a window slot">
        Creates a new window slot. The compositor assigns the protocol
        object identity; no separate window_id is exchanged. The
        compositor will emit configure on the new object to communicate the
        effective initial geometry and state.
      </description>
      <arg name="id"     type="new_id" interface="zweft_shell_window_v1"
           summary="new window object"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string"
           summary="application identifier, reverse-DNS format"/>
      <arg name="title"  type="string"
           summary="initial window title"/>
      <arg name="role"   type="string"
           summary="window role hint (normal, dialog, panel, overlay)"/>
      <arg name="x"      type="int"
           summary="requested x position in compositor logical coordinates"/>
      <arg name="y"      type="int"
           summary="requested y position in compositor logical coordinates"/>
      <arg name="width"  type="int"
           summary="requested width in compositor logical coordinates"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"
           summary="requested height in compositor logical coordinates"/>
    </request>

  </interface>

  <!-- ───────────────────────────── Window ────────────────────────────── -->

  <interface name="zweft_shell_window_v1" version="1">

    <description summary="a compositor-managed window slot">
      Represents one visual window. The compositor controls the effective
      geometry, stacking, and focus state. The shell controls metadata and
      may request geometry changes; the compositor may reject or adjust
      such requests.

      A window object becomes inert after window_closed is received. The
      shell must call destroy on an inert object as soon as possible.
    </description>

    <enum name="state" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="window state bitmask"/>
      <entry name="maximized"  value="1" summary="window occupies full output area"/>
      <entry name="fullscreen" value="2" summary="window covers the entire output including chrome"/>
      <entry name="activated"  value="4" summary="window has input focus"/>
      <entry name="resizing"   value="8" summary="an interactive resize is in progress"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="protocol errors"/>
      <entry name="defunct_window" value="0"
             summary="request sent after window_closed was received"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the window object">
        Destroys the window object. If the window is still alive the
        compositor will remove the corresponding window slot from the
        display. The shell must not send requests on this object after
        calling destroy.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="update_metadata">
      <description summary="update window title and role">
        Updates advisory metadata. The compositor may use these values in
        window decorations or accessibility trees. Updates are not
        authoritative for policy decisions.
      </description>
      <arg name="title" type="string" summary="new window title"/>
      <arg name="role"  type="string" summary="new window role hint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_geometry">
      <description summary="request a geometry change">
        Asks the compositor to change the window geometry. The compositor
        validates the request against output bounds and current policy. The
        compositor is not required to honor the exact values. A configure
        event will be sent with the effective geometry that results.
      </description>
      <arg name="x"      type="int" summary="requested x position"/>
      <arg name="y"      type="int" summary="requested y position"/>
      <arg name="width"  type="int" summary="requested width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="requested height"/>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="compositor sets effective geometry and state">
        Sent by the compositor when the effective geometry or state
        changes. The shell must treat this as authoritative and update its
        DOM layout to match. The shell must ack each configure event by
        sending an update_metadata request or by doing nothing if no
        metadata changed; no explicit ack request is defined in version 1.
      </description>
      <arg name="x"      type="int"  summary="effective x position"/>
      <arg name="y"      type="int"  summary="effective y position"/>
      <arg name="width"  type="int"  summary="effective width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"  summary="effective height"/>
      <arg name="state"  type="uint" summary="bitmask of state enum values"/>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_changed">
      <description summary="input focus state changed">
        Sent when surface-level focus changes for this window slot. The
        shell updates visual focus state in its DOM but does not override
        compositor focus policy.
      </description>
      <arg name="focused" type="uint" summary="1 if focused, 0 if not"/>
    </event>

    <event name="window_closed">
      <description summary="window slot is no longer valid">
        Sent by the compositor when the window object is being invalidated.
        After this event the shell must call destroy on the object. Any
        request sent after window_closed is a protocol error.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="presentation_feedback">
      <description summary="frame presentation timing">
        Sent after a frame containing this window's content is presented
        to the output. Allows the shell to align animations and resize
        flows with compositor timing. tv_sec and tv_nsec are wall-clock
        values from the compositor's monotonic clock. refresh is the
        output refresh interval in nanoseconds; 0 if unknown.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec"   type="uint" summary="seconds component of presentation time"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec"  type="uint" summary="nanoseconds component of presentation time"/>
      <arg name="refresh"  type="uint" summary="output refresh interval in nanoseconds"/>
    </event>

  </interface>

</protocol>
